Never forget why you are the church.
Now, this morning, we're back in our study of Romans, specifically in
a 12th chapter, so go ahead and turn there if you haven't already done so.
We are looking at the impact of the gospel
in our personal ministries.
The way we do church today has caused much confusion.
We cannot help it because I believe this
confusion has been perpetuated for many, many years.
The confusion is this.
Who is supposed to do the work in the church?
Think about it for a second, though.
That's the confusing thing.
I know that here we were educated at Cedar Grove.
You know the right answers, but let's think about the culture of our churches today.
Who is supposed to do the work
traditionally a church will hire out, quote
unquote, notice the quotes, professional, believers
to the work of the ministry?
We would call this a church staff.
Now, before you misinterpret what I'm saying, understand that
ministry staff is necessary and significant
to a growing and thriving local church.
Some people would say that you cannot find ministry staff in the Bible.
Amen?
You know what my response would say?
You can't find a 12 o'clock dismissal time either.
Uh-oh.
When I wrote that, I like that.
Amen?
Here's the thing, it is
a blessing to have call believers who are especially dedicated
vocationally to the ministry of a local church in congregation.
I pray that we're able to grow in our ministry staff
in the coming years to your faithfulness.
But that being true and good does not change the
fact that traditionally, the church sees these
vocational ministry leaders as the beginning
and the end of ministry work.
But as you know, and as many of you just said,
when I ask the question, it takes everyone doing work.
This is why God gifted everyone
in the church for the purpose and way
of building up his church.
It is evident that everyone had a role to play in
the early church, and today, it is no different.
This includes you if you are born again.
So we're going to continue the list that Paul lays out in Romans chapter 12.
We're going to be in verses 6 through 8.
If you're there, say, read.
Having then gifts differing according
to the grace that is given to us, where the prophecy
let us prophecy according to the proportion of faith or ministry that's
serving, let us wait on our ministering, or the he that teacheth
on teaching, or he that exhorteth on exhortation, that's encouragement.
He that giveth, let him do it with simplicity.
He that ruleth with diligence.
And he that showeth mercy with cheerfulness.
We come to the next gift that we see here.
And that is the gift of leadership,
the gift of leadership.
lets pray, Father, I thank you for your word.
I thank you for the name of Jesus.
So God, as I pray to
you right now, God, I just asked you.
To give me the liberty, the power and clarity to preach this message.
God, I pray, Lord, that you pierce our hearts today, God.
God, I pray we can be changed.
If there's somebody here who does not know you.
And I pray they understand that
Jesus lived, died, and rose again so that they could be saved.
So God lets your Holy Spirit do his work.
And it's in Jesus name we pray.
Amen.
And amen.
This may be one of the most misunderstood
gifts in this list, and again, it's been kind of
continued through the years of church, but many
think that the gift of leadership is one that brings about unquestioned authority.
There are those in a church who lead
and do so in a way that is egocentric and quite
honestly corruptive to the body of Christ.
I want you to know that God has never called
anyone to be mean-spirited or my
way or the highway as a leader in the church.
Now, granted, it's his way or no way.
Amen.
But when we come to leadership, we have to understand that it
is not something that gives us the right to hurt or to
offend or to this.
Listen, if we're going to offend, may it be through God's word.
But this misunderstanding comes from a lack of knowledge and what Paul
means by leadership here.
In the KJV, the word is ruleth,
but if you look at the NASB 95, the word is lead.
It says this.
He who leads with diligence.
Now, what does it mean to rule or lead?
Well, if you look at that word in the Greek, it literally
means to guide, lead, and direct.
Now, we see this gift and responsibility
mentioned throughout the entire New Testament.
Paul, in writing to the church in Thessalonica
speaks on those who are in leadership.
He says this in chapter 5, verse 12 through
13, but we request of you, brethren, that you appreciate
those who diligently labor among you and
have charge over you in the Lord and
give you instruction, and that you esteem
them very highly in love because of their work,
live in peace with one another.
Now, I want to say something here that just stuck
out right in my brain.
We see here that it says, and that you esteem them very highly.
We got to be careful with this.
Notice how it says to do so, that
you esteem them very highly in love.
See, what we have, have you ever heard the term don't ever meet your hero?
You ever heard that?
A lot of people, their hero is a spiritual leader
in their life or pastor they have for a long time, whatever it is.
I need you to understand.
I stand before you as a man.
I stand before, a man of God.
I'm saved.
I'm born again, but listen, yes, I have a position of teaching.
I have a position of shepherding the flock, but listen,
if you're going to esteem me highly, please do so in love.
Because I'm going to mess up.
I'm gonna I'm gonna fall.
I'm going to stumble.
And see, what we've done in our culture is we have put these leaders
on these pedestals and we've esteemed them so high,
but it's not in love.
It's just in almost idolatry.
And so in our hero falls, all of a sudden our faith is shattered.
Listen, you don't put your faith in me.
Amen.
You put your faith in Jesus.
The gift that leadership is not for the fan of heart.
What I have found is most people who want the influence
and perceived power of that leadership position.
They don't want what comes with it.
The hard conversations.
The constant expectation to perform and improve,
the burden of decision making.
I don't know why God made me a pastor because he put in me indecisiveness.
Let me just tell you something.
It's the most terrible thing ever.
The heartbreak of disappointment.
The difficulty of guiding people.
Church is typically the leader who finds
out things last, yet is the only one who has to handle the situation.
Everyone else in gossip and go home.
But a leader is left with the mess.
Scripture tells us to appreciate those
who labor, appreciate those who have charge.
That is leadership over you.
I want to take a moment and realize the gravity of the gift of leadership.
The author of Hebrews gives some sobering truth on this burden.
In Hebrews 13, verse 17, obey them that
rule over you and submit yourselves.
For they watch for your souls, as they must
give account that they may do it with joy and not with grief,
for that is unprofitable for you.
In other words, listen, hey, the leaders
are going to have to give account to those who they led, this particular verse
speaks specifically of the office of spiritual
shepherd, but the principle remains for others as well.
I don't want to take this out of context.
I don't want you to come out to me and say, hey, listen, that was about preachers and preachers alone.
No, the principle is for the gift of leadership as well.
That student ministry leader that loses sleep because
their parents allow their students to skip church whenever they
want to or follow the crowd to that trendy youth group across town.
Listen, there's a burden of leadership there.
The children's ministry leader who tirelessly
teaches your children God's word all the while having
to worry about drama and conflict with the parents.
The nursery leader who prays over those
babies and toddlers all the while trying to desperately fill in the
spots of those who simply skip their day because they
knew they had to watch the kids.
So instead of getting filled up, they had to go again for a 5th week in a row.
The worship leaders who prayerfully
and carefully knit together a worship set of God glorifying
songs only to hear the music was too loud or
there wasn't enough hymns or someone wasn't happy with the song.
choice.
That woman's leader
who puts together all the logistics just for their to be petty tension amongst the group.
Church,
I could go on and on and on speaking
on those who labor for you.
Who work and take charge in areas of the
church where leadership is needed.
What a beautiful and oftentimes unappreciated burden.
I know I did not mention
all the leaders we have, but I would like to personally and all those who selflessly
lead in the various ways here at Cedar Grove.
I want to say right now, thank you.
Everyone sees what we do right here.
But very few see what you do everywhere else.
If I can encourage
you in scripture, be Galatians chapter 6, verse 9 and 10.
Let us not lose heart in doing good for in due time, we
will reap if we do not grow weary.
So then while we have opportunity, let us do good to
all people, and especially to those who are the household, of faith.
But we see this term for leader and ruler
used in the qualification of church leadership.
First Timothy chapter 3, verse 4 and five, one that
ruleth well his own house.
Having his children in subjection with all gravity, for
if a man know not how to rule his own house, how shall we take care of the church of God?
Now, this right here is for pastors and deacons
alike, 1st Timothy chapter 3, verse 12, let the
deacons be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children and
their own house as well.
By the way, that's not subjective.
That's scripture.
The gift of leadership is critical to
every in all areas of ministry.
never to say that you have to raise a kid perfect.
If you've done so, we just found out that you were a liar.
Amen.
Let me hang out with your kid for a little bit.
I'll tell you that ain't perfect.
Look, I've taken a lot of your kids to camp.
They ain't perfect.
No, they bad.
I was kidding.
Man, amen.
But
there are a couple important aspects of this gift here.
First, the greatest
leaders in the body of Christ.
Hear me, the greatest leaders in the body of Christ.
Recognize that they are 1st and foremost slaves to Jesus.
You say, what do you mean?
without a proper recognition of place.
A leader in the church, whether it be a leader of a ministry,
whether it be a leader of the church as a whole can quickly become
entitled and arrogant towards others.
Paul,
one of the greatest Christian leaders in scriptures.
Understood this.
Look at what he says about himself in Romans 11,
Paul, a bondservant of Christ Jesus.
called as an apostle,
set apart for the gospel of God.
He emphasizes this yet again in 1st Corinthians chapter one, verse one.
Paul called as an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God.
James, the half-brother of Jesus said this about himself.
James 11, James, a bondservant, a slave of
God, and the Lord Jesus Christ.
Notice how they opened up before they even taught
doctrine of God.
They opened up and said, I'm just a slave of Christ.
Paul
was the greatest church planner the world has ever seen, and
James was what we could call today the senior pastor
of the church in Jerusalem.
The epicenter of the church.
Now, why does this matter?
Well, how did Jesus describe himself?
If we understand that as leaders,
we're all servants of Christ, but sometimes leaders have to be reminded
where their place is.
If we understand that we are bond servants of
Christ, look at what Christ says about himself right here in Philippians
2 or Paul writes about Christ.
Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus.
who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to
be equal with God, but made himself of no reputation,
and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men.
And being found in a fashion as a man, he humbled
himself and became obedient unto death, even
the death of the cross.
Jesus fully God, therefore the creator
of the universe, literally the leader of creation, but
also fully man, obedient as a servant to the will of the Father.
Do you see the model here for leadership?
The greatest leaders are the greatest servants.
And don't miss what I just said.
I know we're real quiet this morning.
That's okay.
The greatest leaders are the greatest servants.
See, a slave can have no arrogance.
A servant has a
servant has nothing to boast about.
Understand a
believer with the get, the leadership has nothing to attribute their skills and
abilities to accept the Lord.
With this principle and truth understood,
we remove the leaders who are overpowering and entitled.
Can I just remind everyone here this morning of something, including myself?
You and I are doing nothing unique here today.
You say, well, hold on, I think
Cedar Grove got a really cool thing going.
Oh, we for sure do.
But what we're doing is not unique.
Whatever gift you are manifesting in
ministry today has been perpetuated by the Holy
Spirit long before you came around.
The gospel that I entrust
to us on a weekly basis is the same gospel
that was entrusted in Paul's time.
I'm speaking to you what has been spoken
for 1000s of years before me.
I'm not special.
But I am called.
There's people in a church that needs that reality check.
The scripture that we need to hear in James
4, tennis says this, humble yourselves in the sight of
the Lord, and he shall lift you up.
I've shared this so many times,
but when I 1st got here,
man, listen, for the 1st 3 or 4 years, I could sit there
and I could tell everyone I've never passed through a church that wasn't growing
in people and money and ministry.
And let me tell you something, I enjoyed knowing that.
I enjoyed the fact that the church that I was leading was growing.
I enjoyed the fact that we were top 10% in baptisms.
I enjoyed the fact that people were asking me questions on how to do things.
I'm like, y'all the joke's on you.
I don't know what I'm doing.
I'm just preaching, but I enjoyed the fact that, hey, things were going good.
But you know what happened?
Before I knew it, Pride got in away.
And you know what God had to do?
God had to humble me.
You
know what happens when God humbles you as a leader?
He teaches you
through that humbling process.
He reveals things to you that should
have been important before, but wasn't, but now they are very important.
Are y'all with me this morning?
We
want to magnify the ministry here at Cedar Grove.
This is going to take humility in all that we do.
If we boast.
Listen, if we boast, which I do believe there is a
biblical model of boasting, it's just in the Lord.
It's what God is doing.
Think about the meaning of the word lead and rule in our text.
Look at the definition again, to guide, to lead, to direct.
These are the 3 pillars of the gift of leadership.
Guide, lead, and direct.
And so knowing this, this brings us to the 2nd
aspect of this gift.
Leadership is for the benefit of others more than even yourself.
I bring us back to the example of Paul.
He wrote this to the church in Philippine.
It says this in Philippians 217, yea, and if
I be offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith,
I joy and rejoice with you all.
See, he fully understand the sacrifice of leading.
In his last letter to Timothy, how did he describe his
ministry in 2nd Timothy chapter 4, verse 6 and 7?
For I'm already being poured out as a drink offering.
And the time my departure has come.
I have fought the good find.
I have finished the course.
I have kept the faith.
You
know, there's a gauge to, Measure your heart.
in leadership.
There's a way to to
see and reveal and expose your heart posture
as a leader in whatever area of life you're leading in.
And it's what makes you quit.
What does it take?
to get you to quit.
Where are the lines that you have drawn
in the sand not because God said so, but because your feelings did.
You know why the average tenure
for a pastor is 3 years?
I'll tell you why, the 1st year is a honeymoon period.
No one cares what you do.
You're the new pastor.
Right?
Now, if you're dumb like me, you start making crazy decisions right out the gate.
And you just test the waters, you know what I'm saying?
You don't know what I'm saying.
I know what I'm saying, but either way,
But the 1st year, man, no one cares.
They just have to have a pastor.
The 2nd year, man, is starting to get used to you.
They're like, man, this dude loves us.
This is this is cool, man.
Year 2 is always it's a sweet year.
As a matter of fact, and for me, year 3 was 2019,
if you were here for 2019, we hung out like every other day.
It was insane.
Literally, at the end of that year, we looked at each other and say, can we not hang out as much?
It was the craziest thing ever.
But listen, what happens on an average tenure
of a pastor, year three, the pastor does this.
Okay.
We have fallen in love with each other.
We know each other now.
There's trust, there's a currency of trust there.
So all of a sudden he says, you know what, God's put in my heart.
going to start leading now.
I'm not just going to preach.
I'm not just gonna, you know, perpetuate some of the traditions that's happened.
No, no, no.
They call me as a leader.
start leading. and before you know it, because change starts to begin.
And that pot gets stirred.
You know what they do?
They turn.
And it's a lot easier for a pastor to leave and for a church to shut down.
You know why there's a desperate need for children, directors and student pastors?
Because these people have
the expectation of doing what a parent is supposed to do.
And so they pour themselves out
so often and they never get poured into because they're so busy.
with the ministry.
You
know how to pour back into a liter, serve alongside them.
Help them.
Submit to the vision and strategy
God has put on their heart.
See, when this comes together, it creates joy.
Look again at Philippians 2.17.
But even if I am being poured out as a drink offering upon the
sacrifice and service of your faith, I rejoice
and share my joy with you all.
But see, then we get to 2nd
Timothy, the tone is different.
There is a finale that Paul's writing.
The reason is evident.
He knows Paul knows that he is about to be executed
for his faith.
He is going to be a martyr for Christ.
His ministry is coming to an end.
Not because he was quitting, but rather because he
was about to enter into rest.
His work was done, his work was completed.
And so he compared his life.
He looks back at the ministry of him serving Christ, and
he compares it as a drink offering poured upon the
altar, for I'm now ready to be offered.
And the time my departure is at hand.
I fought a good fight.
I finished my course.
I have kept the faith.
I want to be vulnerable with you
Today, and listen, again, I know I understand.
I'm saying some of these things because when people think of a leader in a church,
They instantly think, pastor.
And I believe this gift goes so far beyond the pulpit.
But I've made many mistakes in
leadership here at Cedar Grove.
I have led well and have not led so well.
There are things I have said and done that I
wish I could take back, man, I think about them all the time.
There have been times where
I felt it best to hanging up and do something else.
Stop taking the phone calls,
stop being the one who hears all the bad news.
Stop being so burdened with all the situations, stop
being the only one fighting for other people's marriages.
Stop speaking to the students at the schools, weekend, week
out because no one else cares.
Stop so often taking time for my family forever else's family.
There are times that I would just, you know what?
I can do something else.
Let me go get a 9 to 5 clock in, clock out, go home and forget about it.
Because
in leadership in a church, it's not how that works.
I don't care if you're in whatever ministry you're leading.
That is not how it works.
But may I encourage you those
who are tired and weary today.
Look back at Romans 12 verse 8.
It says he that ruleth with diligence.
You know what that word diligence means?
To do one's best.
When
I get to thinking about quitting and giving up, I remember how God gave his best.
And only begotten for me.
I get to thinking about the one who called me,
the one who faced the greatest task in human history, the one who
was the only way, the one who asked the Father.
If there was any other way.
Let this cup pass for me.
Yet he submitted himself to the will of the Father.
I think of Jesus shedding his
perfect, precious blood, his blood pouring out so that I can be saved.
He
lived an entire life just so I could Live mine.
He died the death he died so that I could live life.
Church when ministry, when your gift in this becomes more of
a burden than a blessing.
Remember the why.
You say, what do you mean by that?
Well, are you tired?
Remember why we labor?
Are you discouraged?
Remember why we serve?
Are you ready to quit?
Remember why.
When we forget, we find ourselves pouring out ourselves and becoming empty.
When we forget to remember.
We continuously poor.
The extra study time, even though no one shows
up to hear it, we are pouring ourselves out, the difficult conversations
that we that turns our stomach,
we pour out, the seemingly unanswered prayers,
although we pray time and time again.
We're pouring ourselves out, the discouragement of feeling like the only
one who really cares, we're pouring ourselves out, the
constant back and forth of highs and lows.
We're pouring ourselves out.
The feeling of not being appreciated.
The never ending labor and ministry.
We consistently as leaders pour ourselves out.
But what happens when we remember why?
We cling to Jesus.
He pours back into us.
We stay unified with other believers.
We get poured back into.
We remain connected to our church family.
We stay consistent in the word.
We get poor back into.
We focus on the mission, we get poured back into.
We begin to see the bumps in the road as signs of effectiveness rather
than reasons to give up.
We get poured back into.
We begin to look at things eternally rather than temporarily.
We get a renewed vision of why we're doing what we're doing.
We get poured back into.
You
know what happens to somebody that's empty?
They
begin to look at life from the outside looking in.
I
believe there are so many believers that are trying their best, that are trying
in diligence to lead and to serve others and
to make ministries happen and to grow ministries.
And what they're doing is they're drying up on the vine.
It's supposed to be connected to this church.
And you know what we do?
How many kids you bring in a children's church?
Well that's kind of low.
Hey, what's your numbers
on the hill every Wednesday night?
Well, that's kind of low.
Well, what are you not working?
Are you not doing your job?
What's going on?
Little do we know that they're literally pouring themselves out.
You say, what does this have to do with Jesus?
Well, you see here,
What
even is a drink offering?
See,
Paul is using the language of a drink offering.
I'm pouring myself out.
The 1st instance of a
drink offering was in Genesis 35, verse 14.
And it says this and Jacob set up a
pillar in a place where he talked with him, even a pillar of stone, and he
poured a drink offering thereon, and he poured oil thereon.
Now, see, we have to understand that everything
in the Old Testament points to Christ.
Jacob had just wrestled with God.
Jacob literally, God was changing his name as he who wrestles with God.
All the way back when God
changed Jacob's name to Israel, and the 1st recorded drink
offering took place, it was not Jacob that was the point,
even though he was going to lead God's people, even though that God had a
plan for him, he was the covenant keep, but it wasn't him.
It wasn't Israel name.
It was God.
Jesus was the point.
How do we know this?
Okay?
Well, remember, drink offering.
We're going to skip to Luke 22, verse 20.
This is what Jesus says.
And in the same way, he took the cup after they had eaten, saying, this
cup, which is poured out for you is the new covenant
in my blood.
Understand something.
Jesus, the one who led captivity captive, the one who defeated
death hell in the grave, the one who lived a life of no sin for our sake.
How did he do this?
He did so by pouring himself out.
By the way, another word for poor is to shed.
Why should that be
important to us because Jesus shed his blood so that we could be forgiven.
We
do what we do because Jesus did what he did.
And
so this morning, I just, again, I'm just asking you.
A
healthy church has people that serve in every possible way
through the gifts.
We have another gift of mercy that we're going to talk about next week.
But so many people.
They want to just sit here and say, okay, well, you know, that's the gifts and you
got to pick one and understand this.
All the 3 main lists that we have of gifts.
They all have different ones and they all mention one here and
they don't mention what's that saying is that the Holy Spirit is not limited.
in how he can use us.
But there are certain gifts that we
know we can have, and we know that others do have.
So this morning, listen, if you're serving Christ, maybe
it be with the gift of leadership.
Maybe it be a gift that maybe no one sees, or maybe it just be a gift of help.
So whatever the gifts that we've talked about.
If you're serving Christ and you're thinking, man, I'm unappreciated.
I'm unseen.
No one cares about what's going on.
Again, I want to read to you again, Galatians.
Let us not lose heart in doing good.
For in due time, we will reap if we do not grow
weary.
You know why we celebrate baptism so much like we do?
Because it reminds us of why we're doing what we're doing.
So then while we have opportunity, let
us do good to all people.
And especially to those who are the household of faith.
Who is the household of faith, it's the church.
So I wonder if you're tired and weary.
Maybe you're maybe you're like I've
been before my past and you're just ready to give up and go home.
You just ready to just call it quits.
And by the way, I want to say something to this.
If you're hearing all this and
you're thinking, man, I have never experienced that, you need to get the serving Jesus.
There's
too many people in the church that watch everyone else get dried up in the vine.
don't say a thing about it.
They may gossip about it.
They may slander about it, but they don't do a thing about it.
They sit there their entire life doing nothing for the Lord.
Let me just tell you something.
You out of God's will.
God never called you to sit in a pew, ever.
Ever.
God called you to serve him through the church.
But maybe you do relate what I'm saying.
Maybe you are tired.
I was going to ask you this morning not to lose heart.
You know, I don't
know why God does what he does in the in the way he does it.
I mean, I do.
It's for his glory.
Amen, for his plan and good and perfect will.
But think about it.
We come to this gifted leadership.
We talk about this like we have.
For many of us, you're about to have the most
exhausting week of your year.
Unless you're going to church camp, then
that's even more exhausting.
But for many of you, you're going to have the most exhausting week of the year.
And right around Wednesday, you know
what's going to start happening to you and get cranky.
You're going to start getting irritated.
And that's when we remember why we're doing what we're doing.
I don't know the numbers,
but we have, we have like 24th
and 5th graders coming to VBS this week already registered.
Pray for those teachers.
Amen?
But listen, as you're leading those
4th and 5th graders to every which way on our campus and going to
wreck and doing this and doing that,
Let's not forget why.
Let's not forget to love them.
Let's not figure to show them
that, hey, listen, hey, yeah, I'm tired, but I'm here for you.
I want to serve you in love.
Don't forget, when you see someone,
it might be looking stressed out, it might be kind of bewildered of all of it.
Hey, it's okay to go to someone and say, hey, look, I see what you're doing.
I appreciate it.
Guys, we got to start appreciating each other.
We got to start getting with one accord.
So with Hezbot, our eyes closed over this place.